Okay, next section, pulmonary infections.
The key discussion here is going to deal with pneumonia.
Pneumonia is an infection of the lung parenchyma.
It occurs when the normal defenses are impaired.
Some of the normal defenses include our cough reflex.
If that's impaired, there's an increased risk.
Of course, the idea here would be that we're not able to remove organisms and particles
that we would normally cough up.
Damage to the mucociliary escalator can increase the risk for pneumonia.
Recall that our lung conducting system that brings air into the lung
is actually lined by respiratory epithelium, and respiratory epithelium is ciliated.
Now, those cilia are important because they beat upward and allow us to push the mucus
that's present in the conducting portion of the lung up along the airway
and then back down the throat so that we swallow the mucus that is normally produced.
Now, that's important because it helps us to clear anything that might be trapped within that mucus.
And so damage to the mucociliary escalator would increase the risk for pneumonia.
Now, some examples of how you might damage that escalator would be if the patient has a viral pneumonia.
That would damage the respiratory epithelial cells, and then because there is no mucociliary escalator,
there would be an increased risk of developing a superimposed bacterial pneumonia on top of that viral pneumonia.
And we'll talk about that in more detail as we move forward.
Mucus plugging also increases the risk.
For example, you know that any time you block a tube, in pathology, the general principle is that you get infection behind the block.
And so mucus plugging would result in blocking of an airway, which would then increase the risk of infection distal to that block.
clinically, the patients who have pneumonia present with fever and chills.
That's because the organisms often leak out into the blood, which then results in fever and chills.
There can be cough with yellow-green or rusty sputum.
The yellow-green would represent pus, and the rusty sputum representing blood.
Tachypnea with pleuritic chest pain can also be seen.
This is particularly important, the pleuritic chest pain.
The idea here is that when you breathe in, you are stretching the pleura, and when you stretch the pleura, you get pain.
And so that's called pleuritic chest pain, chest pain that arises when a patient expands the lung and stretches the pleura.
Of course, the pleura is enervated, and what would sensitize these particular nerves in this region
would be the presence of bradykinin and prostaglandin E2 that's generated by the inflammatory response.
It's, of course, high yield to know that bradykinin and prostaglandin E2 are your two key mediators of pain.
And then the patients will have decreased breath sound with dullness to percussion.
The idea here is that the lung is like a drum, it's full of air.
If you replace the air with consolidation due to the production of exudate from the inflammatory response,
that exudate will then decrease the breath sounds in that region, along with resulting in a dullness to percussion.
And finally, the white count will be elevated because the patient is infected, so you would expect to see an elevated white blood cell count.
Diagnosis is often made by performing chest x-ray.
Sputum gram stain can help to identify a bacteria, along with culture, which can help to subtype that.
Blood cultures are also useful because organisms will often be in the blood, as I've mentioned just a moment ago.
Now, classically on chest x-ray, there are three patterns that can be seen.
And the first pattern would be where the pneumonia produces consolidation that takes over an entire lobe, and so that is called a lobar pneumonia.
Another possibility would be that you have consolidation that runs along the small airways, so it would be distributed in a patchy manner along the small airways,
and that's called a bronchopneumonia, and then the third possibility is where you don't have consolidation, but instead you have inflammation within the interstitium of the lung.
And, of course, the interstitium is the connective tissue of the alveolar air sac, and that's called an interstitial pneumonia,
and the key pattern seen in an x-ray would be an increase in the lung markings, as if you're seeing, as if the interstitium of all of these air sacs becomes slightly more visible,
so you begin to see an increase in the markings of the lung, and I'll make all this very clear as we move forward on a couple sample x-ray images.
Now, important to note that when you think about lobar pneumonia and bronchopneumonia, which I've drawn here on the left, these are usually going to be bacterial.
And then when you think about interstitial pneumonia, this is also called atypical pneumonia, and the organisms are not usually bacterial,
but you think about perhaps virus, and you'll see this as we move forward as well.
Lobar pneumonia is a consolidation of the entire lobe, as I've already illustrated. Again, it's usually bacterial, as I've already stated as well.
Most important to note on this particular slide is that the two most common causes of lobar pneumonia are strep pneumoniae,
which represents about 95% of lobar pneumonia, and then Klebsiella, which is a very high yield bug to be aware of for the purposes of examinations especially.
Now, here's what a lobar pneumonia looks like. I've already highlighted this principle.
You get knockout of a lobe with consolidation, hence the term lobar pneumonia.
Now, were you to look at this under a slide, what you would see is that the air sacs, these circles here that I'm drawing,
they represent the air sacs, and you can see that the air sacs are full of neutrophils,
which are all these cells present in the air sacs, along with this pink frothy material,
which represents the exudate of the pneumonia.
And so, of course, if this was present within all the air sacs of a lobe, you would have wipe out of a lobe,
and hence the picture that we just saw, which was the lobar pneumonia.
Now, again, I've told you that the two key causes, 95% is streptococcus pneumoniae,
and as is stated in your text, this is the most common cause of community-acquired pneumonia,
classically seen in middle-aged adults and the elderly.
So streptococcus pneumoniae, 95% of lobar pneumoniae.
Kleptococcus pneumoniae represents about 5% of lobar pneumoniae,
and what's the highest yield to understand about this is that it is an enteric flora that is aspirated.
So it's classically going to be seen in patients at increased risk for aspiration.
For example, elderly in nursing homes, alcoholics, these people are at increased risk for aspiration,
and so those are the classic patients that get Kleptococcus pneumoniae.
Now, important to note that this bug has a thick mucoid capsule,
and so when these patients present, they often present with current jelly sputum,
because part of what they cough up is this thick mucoid capsule.
Now, Kleptococcus pneumoniae often is complicated by an abscess,
so it's not uncommon for patients with Klebsiella to also develop an abscess.
So those are some of the high yields to be aware of, especially for board examinations.
Now, when a patient gets a lobar pneumonia, there are four classic phases that can be seen on pathology.
The first is congestion, and the idea here is when you get infection,
you're going to congest the blood vessels by dilating those blood vessels,
increasing the amount of blood in the vessels, and also resulting in edema.
So the very first phase is congestion, where you have congested vessels and edema.
The second phase is called red hepatization.
The idea here is that you develop an exudate within the lung.
The exudate contains neutrophils and some blood, and that fills the alveolar air sacs,
and it gives the normal spongy lung a solid consistency,
and so hence the term hepatization, or liver-like change to the normal spongy lung.
And, of course, it's red here because there's a lot of red blood cells that are also coming out into the alveolar airspace.
Eventually, those red blood cells are broken down, and so it turns gray, and then we call that gray hepatization.
And finally, you resolve the exudate, and then you begin healing, and that's called resolution.
Very high yield to note that after a patient gets pneumonia,
you pretty much heal the lung by regenerating the tissue that was normally present.
And remember that the type 2 pneumocyte, very high yield, the type 2 pneumocyte is the stem cell of the lung
that helps to regenerate the lining of the alveolar air sacs.
Here's what a pneumonia would look like on gross exam.
This represents the consolidated lobe, and so you can see that it becomes solid instead of spongy,
and so that's where the term hepatization comes from, where it becomes much more like the liver than it does the normal spongy lung.
And in this particular case, this is all full of red blood cells, and so this is red hepatization.
Once the red cells are broken down, this would then turn gray, become gray hepatization, and finally it would resolve.
Bronchopneumonia is when you get scattered patchy consolidation centered around bronchioles.
It's often multifocal and bilateral, and again, as I've stated, it's caused by bacteria.
Here's a classic picture showing you a bunch of splotches or areas of pneumonia, and again, that would represent a bronchopneumonia.
Here's a gross picture of bronchopneumonia highlighting the patchiness of the process, and of course, this is running along the bronchioles.
So scattered along the bronchioles are these patches of inflammation.
Now the key causes of bronchopneumonia include staph aureus, very high yield to note a few things, and I've listed them here.
The first is that it is the most common cause of secondary pneumonia.
Recall that secondary pneumonia is when you have bacterial pneumonia superimposed on a pre-existing viral infection of the lung.
And again, the idea here is that the virus knocks out the mucociliary escalator.
That increases the risk to develop a pneumonia.
The patients subsequently get infected with staph aureus, and that again results in what we call a secondary pneumonia.
Staph aureus is often complicated by abscess or empyema, which refers to pus in the plural space, and that's important to note as well.
H-flu is another important cause of bronchopneumonia.
This is a common cause of secondary pneumonia, which we've already talked about, and pneumonia superimposed on COPD.
So this can result in, in patients with COPD, they can get superimposed pneumonia, which then leads to exacerbation of the COPD.
Pseudomonas aeruginosa can also cause a bronchopneumonia.
The classic patient who develops this is the cystic fibrosis patient.
Moraxella can create a bronchopneumonia.
This would be seen as a community-acquired pneumonia and a pneumonia that could be superimposed on COPD, again leading to an exacerbation of COPD.
And then finally, legionella is an important cause of community-acquired pneumonia.
It can also result in pneumonia superimposed on COPD or pneumonia in immunocompromised states.
Very high yield to note for legionella is that it often arises from a water source.
And then also important to note is that it is an intracellular organism that is best visualized by silver stain.
A third pattern of pneumonia is interstitial pneumonia, and this is when you get diffuse interstitial infiltrates within the lung.
Of course, the interstitium, as I've already explained, is a connective tissue of the alveolar air sac.
So if these are the alveolar air sacs, you begin to have inflammation within the wall of the alveolar air sacs without any major consolidation.
Interstitial pneumonia is often also called atypical pneumonia, and the word atypical helps me to remember a few things about interstitial pneumonia.
First of all, the signs and symptoms are relatively atypical.
Remember that in the classic patient with pneumonia, you would expect high fever, chills, pleuritic chest pain, dullness to percussion, an elevated white blood cell count, etc.
However, in interstitial pneumonia, the symptoms are much more upper respiratory symptoms, so that the patients have minimal sputum, they have cough, and they usually have a low fever.
Here's a classic image for an interstitial pneumonia.
When you look at the lung, you can clearly see that the interstitium is much more prominent, and you can clearly see that there's an increase in lung markings and interstitial processes occurring.
Here's a picture of interstitial pneumonia on biopsy, and what you would see is that the air sacs are predominantly empty.
You don't see very many cells or much of an exudate within the air sacs.
However, instead, you see a lot of inflammatory cells within the wall of the interstitium.
And again, it's this interstitial process that results in the increased markings on x-ray.
The other thing that the word atypical helps me to remember when I consider an interstitial pneumonia is that the bugs are usually atypical.
They're not your classic pneumonia bugs.
The most common cause of atypical pneumonia is mycoplasma pneumonia.
It's important to note that it usually affects young adults, classically military recruits or college students living in a dorm.
One of the high-yield complications to be aware of is that it can produce an autoimmune hemolytic anemia.
That's going to be an IgM, and so that's called a cold agglutinin, so it's one type of autoimmune hemolytic anemia.
And finally, important to note that it's not usually visible on gram stain because it lacks a cell wall.
So these are all the high-yields concerning mycoplasma.
Chlamydia pneumonia is the second most common cause of atypical pneumonia in young adults.
So if you have a young adult with the signs and symptoms of an atypical pneumonia and it's not mycoplasma, you want to think about chlamydia pneumonia.
RSV is the most common cause of atypical pneumonia in infants.
CMV is the classic cause of atypical pneumonia in patients who want post-transplant immunosuppressive therapy.
Influenza is a classic cause of atypical pneumonia in the elderly.
It can also be seen in the immunocompromised and those with pre-existing lung disease.
Very high-yield to know that patients who get influenza, they increase their risk for secondary pneumonia.
This is very important to understand because the vast majority of patients who get influenza virus as a cause of pneumonia
that don't die because of the flu virus, they don't die because of the influenza virus.
Instead what happens is the influenza virus weakens the normal defenses and that allows for a secondary bacterial pneumonia
which then kills the patient.
And so it's important to note that Staph aureus is the most common cause of secondary pneumonia in patients who have influenza virus pneumonia.
Coxiella is an important cause of atypical pneumonia in farmers and veterinarians.
It's classically associated with a high fever so it's called Q fever.
Remember that normally when you think about interstitial pneumonia the fever is usually low
and so it's important to note that these patients would have a high fever and hence the term Q fever.
Now what happens in these particular patients is they get exposed to Coxiello spores
and that's because those spores are deposited on the cattle by ticks or are present in cattle placentas.
And so if a cattle recently gave birth the placenta could potentially be a source of infection.
Now remember that from microbiology that Coxiello is actually a rickettsial organism
but it's different from most other rickettsiae because number one it causes pneumonia, that's unique.
Number two it does not require an arthropod vector, it survives as a heat resistant spore.
And number three it doesn't produce a skin rash whereas most rickettsial organisms would.
Aspiration pneumonia occurs in patients who are at risk for aspiration, for example alcoholics or patients who are comatose.
This is classically due to anaerobic bacteria from the oropharynx
and the three high yield bugs to be aware of are Bacterioides, Fusobacterium and Peptococcus.
These are commonly asked on examinations.
Recall that when patients get aspiration pneumonia the classic location is the right lower lobe
which then results in an abscess and the right lower lobe is the classic location
because anatomically the right main stem bronchus branches at a less acute angle than the left.
So if this is the main airway and then you're looking at the branch, this is the right and the left is the right
lower lobe is for example like that.
So it's much easier to go down the right than it is to go down the left
which then results in a right lower lobe abscess.
The last of the pulmonary infections that we're going to discuss is tuberculosis.
This arises with inhalation of aerosolized mycobacterium tuberculosis.
Remember that when a patient gets exposed to TB they get primary TB.
Now in primary TB the patient gets focal caseating necrosis in the lung,
usually the lower lobe and also within the hyalur lymph nodes.
Of course these foci are going to undergo fibrosis and calcification
and that results in formation of something called the gon complex
which is basically a area of fibrosis and calcification
indicating that the patient has been exposed to primary TB.
Now recall that primary TB is usually asymptomatic
so all the classic signs and symptoms of TB will not occur with this initial exposure
but the PPD will become positive.
Of course the only real complication of primary TB is the formation of a gon complex
that is a fibrosed and calcified nodule that arises within the lung.
It's classically subplural so notice out here this is the pleura
and this represents the gon complex.
Now patients usually develop a gon complex within the subplural region of the lung
along with the hyalur lymph nodes.
Over time this gon complex can become reactivated
and that would then result in secondary TB.
Now this commonly arises due to AIDS.
It can also be seen with aging
and of course you know that because of AIDS
there's been an increase in the incidence of tuberculosis.
Often it occurs at the apex of the lung
and that's because the oxygen tension is highest at the apex of the lung.
Now once a patient gets reactivation then they develop foci of caseous necrosis
they can also develop miliary pulmonary TB
where you've got tiny little regions of TB
that are sort of scattered across the entire lung
or they can develop a bronchopneumonia due to TB
so they would get this classic bronchopneumonia pattern
but of course this would be due to TB.
Clinically these are the patients that present with fever and night sweats
cough with hemoptysis, weight loss, eventually a biopsy would be performed
and it would reveal caseating granulomas.
And of course the differential diagnosis of caseating granulomas
includes fungus and TB.
And so an AFB stain would be performed
and that would reveal the presence of red acid-fast bacilli.
This is the classic picture of a caseating necrotic granuloma.
You can see the necrosis within the center of this granuloma
along with the epithelioid histiocytes out here at the edge.
Of course you would perform an AFB stain
to confirm which organism is involved
and in this particular case you can clearly see these red slender organisms
which represent mycobacterium.
Now remember that TB can also spread to multiple distant sites within the body.
It can basically spread to any tissue.
However there are a few high yield tissues to be aware of.
First of all it can go to the meninges giving a patient meningitis
and important to remember that when it goes to the meninges
it usually involves the meninges at the base of the brain.
That's particularly high yield.
So meningitis with granulomas at the base of the brain.
It can also involve the cervical lymph nodes.
The most common organ to be involved is the kidney
and when it involves the kidney it often produces a sterile pyuria.
And finally when it goes to the bone we call that pock disease
in particular when it involves the lumbar vertebral bodies.
And so these are some of the key sites of spread outside of the lung.
And that concludes our discussion of pulmonary infection.
All right, let's go to the test.
Invest in the video.
Okay, let's go to the next slide.
The next slide…
I'll talk to you.
We'll talk to you soon.
Now let's talk about the test.
We'll talk about the test.
OK, so let's see that.
Okay, so if you're the test.
This turned up on the test.
This tumor can be taken from and you can see a patient.